welcome to the first app prototype
planning session thank you for joining
for now it's just me and Bentley we will
start off talking I guess about some
general questions and thoughts to do
with sort of planning I guess the tech
stack behind an app that sort of thing
and I believe that Matus will be joining
us shortly and we can dive into
specifics on this particular project
which is the prototype for wiki election
for the most part I'm just playing the
role of like the idea person there's not
actually a developer which i think is a
role that a lot of people in the game be
project space identify with so I like
that role and Bentley you can be you
were you actually know you're a
developer and a project manager and that
sort of things so you'll have a lot more
useful stuff to say than I probably will
even know what to ask about so yeah it's
really helpful when two people from two
different perspectives talk so I think
it'd be really helpful you know even
kind of did to start it off I I guess
one thing I'd like to say is that every
project is different and so often times
when I hear advice like this people say
oh well you need to like do an MVP first
and I'm like wow when they created the
lightbulb they did a thousand tests
before they put it in anyone's home
because I couldn't get it to last more
than 20 minutes right so some things you
can prototype quickly and some things
you can't you know if you're developing
a vaccine you have to invest a year into
it before you actually well at several
months before you can even do trials on
skin cells and then you do it on you
know animals and then humans so
everybody is a little bit different but
we could definitely use wiki election as
an example and then I can also talk a
little bit about reason score and stuff
but I drew how was the process for you
so far so just so people know you've
been building prototypes and no code
solutions right yeah and then now you're
doing your first prototype
a custom-built and Marta she's been
doing that
so how's what have you learned so far in
the process um I mean the no code
solutions were definitely good to sort
of act as a proof of concept I find that
in general trying to explain software
like even you know working at a software
company working with people who are used
to working with my software trying to
explain software almost never works like
unless you've got something to show them
and mock-ups help but even that's pretty
limited like I would say sort of you
know mock-ups like just an image of how
it might look is kind of like the bare
bones like don't even try to explain it
if you don't have that it's because
that's really hard and then the further
along that path you go the easier is
going to be to explain so like you know
started out with mock-ups and then I
sort of used those to guide myself to
figure out what can I build in these no
code solutions and that's where it
started to make a bit more sense I think
the people where they were able to go in
there and look and jump around it does
get hard to explain like the really
unique elements where no code solutions
tend to be pretty basic and just sort of
show off like here's a database here's
you know showing fields from from
records which still helps I think for a
lot of people to picture how you would
navigate what kind of information you
would show but that's definitely where
some of the limitations hit for the no
code solutions I find is a it it's
definitely better than just a static
mock-up but I'm getting to the point now
where I'm starting to you know I want to
do some of the more unique elements and
actually have it be like a full coated
solution that will actually allow people
to register his numbers and be a bit
more streamlined then you want to build
which yes the other part it was hard
because there's so many of them up there
that I did some early research I found
knack it seemed to do a pretty good job
on some other stuff and it worked so I
sort of delve into that and for lack of
a better term committed to using that
and then found that there was a bunch of
other no code
platforms that maybe would have been
better but I did find it like okay I've
got my no code one it's you know twenty
percent of the way there that's good
enough for a no code I still sort of
poked and prodded them to see if there
was anything like oh I actually could
use this like they make their real
prototype I haven't found any no code
solutions that I'm that confident in
that I could actually build like a
usable you know the first real version
to get actual users on and start doing
data entry I didn't feel confident
enough in any of that you know goat
solutions yeah yeah as far as no code
solutions of hoping a developer friend
build a out of community site she has
tried web flow bubble and is now using
app Guyver the challenge she's been
having is getting a community login so
that people can sign up kinda like a
social media site create their own
content and then share it manage content
which Pollione them with your thing
which is funny because I'm now thinking
I thought bubble actually had examples
of a social media site so I might have
to go back and look and see how they
handled the authentication for that
right so she really likes app divert
from a design standpoint web flow was
pretty good from a design standpoint
bubble was horrific
from a UI standpoint but had really good
kind of back-end and stuff right and
they may have had a they may have
already had the member management system
I can't remember but with app cover app
Guyver hasn't better open to the public
for very long and then I've struggled
for the last two weeks to get a
membership system integrated that
includes login from like the specific
tool is for business people so we wanted
to LinkedIn login and there you cannot
do it without having another your own
back-end somewhere in there you can't
use off the 0 we have a bug that they're
going to fix you can't you
is the link in direct login because you
do need some sort of back-end for that
right and they're back in won't work for
it someone else has gotten oh it is a
firebase from Google working as a login
but that's what you type in using an ID
and password he didn't try to get it
that they do support like LinkedIn and
other things right but I think you're
gonna have the same problem as the
office zero solution so I mean for her
specific situation I'm probably gonna go
ahead and just set up username and
password log in later on we'll get it
integrated with LinkedIn and AB divers
is about to implement a login system so
that's probably getting down into much
of the weeds but I think a lot of the
apps that people are producing is some
form of community app I think if you
were just gonna do a Content app these
days you know you content site you know
there's Squarespace and and there's
there's tons right I mean if you're just
gonna be doing it yourself as the
backend you mean right yeah totally yet
like if you just have a website or a
wordpress or however yeah right if you
don't have any real features and it's
just content I think everyone's got that
settled so I can't think of many things
the only time you'd really need a no
code solution I think is is some sort of
community based content which surprises
me then that none of these systems have
a I'm just taking through this live on
air now these places really have a good
community system and then there are
complete community sites like what was
it bell there was something Bell I can't
remember it was anyways but they're kind
of like kind of like slack and stuff
like that but I have a little bit more
features but they'd but they won't have
what you need which is both community
login and really straight customized
features right exactly and that's one of
the areas where nack actually is pretty
good is the like
the database side of knack I didn't see
any of the apps out there were as good
now app Guyver it sounds like could
connect to air table which I haven't
played with but I believe that alone
should have a lot of the features that I
probably want but neck does have sort of
member registration and one of the
things I like is that if you get into
the paid version I think technically
even the free version allows this but
you're limited to how many records you
have all of your member logins just
count as records so which is quite nice
look if you actually trying to build it
up fairly large and in the prototype for
the game view projects the together tech
thing I kind of have a bit more lockdown
and I haven't played too much with the
trying to streamline that but like the
the database side and the member part is
decent the UI it isn't as good as the
other options that you shall meet the UI
on those is way better yeah yeah but it
has really good kind of table and
reporting it seems and actually me and
carry the person is what I was talking
about are going to be doing a local no
code meetup group so we'll be doing it
locally and we posting that content on
YouTube and stuff so people nice
so we'll start consulting on no code
engagements help people get set up and
stuff like that so and is that more how
to use a specific one like here's how to
use app divert or is it starting out
with like here's the options here's how
to compare them yeah we're gonna start
from there but then when we kind of pick
the ones that made our needs those are
the ones we're going to end up being
focusing on but but I think there will
be a lot of times doing comparisons I'm
kind of figuring out although I checked
on Twitter and you know I followed one
no code person or our own no code sight
and then it suggested people I was like
oh I'll follow that and then I was like
it like 20 and I'm like oh right
apparently this is popular so I don't
know no worse probably could have done a
better job with scheduling this ahead of
time and pushing that here in fishing
out there so my poll
so yeah but Tish we were just going
through general kind of no code
solutions and Adriel progress so far in
trying to get his app from but from idea
to concept MVP Minimum Viable Product
for anything and that's watching
although it's just reading a post about
minimum lovable product which is
interesting but that that to me is
beyond Minimum Viable Product right and
and even before Minimum Viable Product I
was realizing that there's a minimum
learn about experiment alright which
there's I think there's an official term
for that and that's not it but something
like that or you know run small
experiments which is where I am and
reason score and Marty sure I was
talking about that each kind of project
has its own kind of R&D kind of phase
some are big some are small you know
what they are a recent scores got a huge
R&D phase wiki election wasn't as big
but still had its own so so I'm not a
drone now that Mar - she's here we could
focus on the wiki election yeah I guess
or a transition from the no code to the
next step which is the code of one so
that actually kind of perfect timing
just on the note of the MVP one of the
of the things that I find when I talk to
people about it is this notion of like
it almost feels that people think that's
the first sort of attempt at like really
okay that's the first thing that that
we're gonna test and like with you know
I I you and I have briefly discussed you
know agile you kind of start out with
like as you sort of said like the
minimums or a learning experiment and
then you keep building it until it
becomes viable and then you'll sort of
know that during testing and actually as
you actually start to use it you're like
oh people would use this you know yeah
oh yeah the terms are a bit kind of
floppy and used around everywhere like
there's a website called quick MVP
but all that website is is a landing
page where you where people kicking son
say yes I'd like to do it and then you
have no product behind it and that so
you're really just testing your
description of your concept right and
see and also you tend to buy traffic or
at least with what used to be but you
buy traffic from Google so you're
checking your ability to pay for
customers right which is to me as a
minimum viable experiment right kind of
like a proof of concept if I were to
build this would you want in right I can
see how that's valuable but yet not
really I'm deep ei right yeah at all
yeah okay yeah this we talked a bit
about the no code solution personally I
still recommend starting there that's
definite like as I built it as I saw
some of the UI even though it wasn't
perfect I still learned stuff and I you
know updated my design I'm like oh that
actually doesn't look that good when
you're using it or oh the brick there's
a screen in between this one and that
one so that did that did you have no
helped I think as the pension if it is
going to be more like member facing it
doesn't sound like anyone here is aware
of a really good no code solution that
supports that so that might be a reason
to sort of still do no code but you
might not be there very long before you
start wanting to get into actually I
would it sold out
I think the future will be a no code or
low code really right and and I was just
realizing I've done low code for 20
years now cuz I was using access to oh
okay first no code platforms because you
could create an app put it on someone's
desk top and we used them and I didn't
write a single interesting it wasn't
web-based of course but okay yeah but I
mean I was technically an echo yeah I
totally agree that that's where things
are headed like in my day job I helped
manage sales force and that's like you
know enterprise levels CRM where their
instruction is like clicks not code if
you can avoid using code do it just use
our platform and you can do a lot so I
think as you start to see these like not
billion-dollar companies start to
improve their platforms and you're
totally right
we'll get to a point where it's almost
like a mix of you know app Guyver and
like Ruby on Rails we can actually make
a good somewhat stable relatively
performance you know okay app was just
you know clicking and dragging and
connecting your components yeah and then
the developers will be focusing more on
building out components of building
these systems right and then making
customized widgets that that the the
unique parts of each right yeah so sort
of like the I guess so similar to the
these helpers model of you want to go
clicks nut code but in some cases you
still need code it's not still it's not
reasonable to completely exclude it but
trying to to limit it well a lot of
companies will have their their unique
proposition and a lot of times that will
require some sort of right yeah because
if you can just click and drag it then
there's not really a unique proposition
its unique in that I'm the only one that
there's drag this component onto this
page so do you think it'd be helpful if
Marty walked us through his yeah yeah I
guess or even just like the like what
went into your decisions of like what
you know tech pieces to use anything
else that you know you may be a decision
that you made in getting the the current
prototype to where it is and stuff that
maybe we haven't covered yet or the
people who watch this at some point
might be interested to in a motor be
interesting to yeah also since you know
since we are kind of helping other
people what what decisions you may made
differently based on your discussions
with Adria or his unique situation might
be cool okay so my decisions driven by
the stuff I know so because I know react
and its components and bits and pieces
and from what I know react is one of the
fastest system called but still
prototyping the so obviously I decided
to use that I people have good
experiences with Ruby on Rails but
that's I'm not as proficient in in that
react was was the choice then in my
previous projects even with prototypes
just prototypes I did use some
relational relational database like
Postgres which usually was like half of
the project to get the database right
and to create basically back-end and in
this case and in my recent prototypes
I used firebase which is not relational
but it doesn't need to be in most cases
so to create a quick prototype it's it's
really straightforward and easy and
quick to just install just to create
like a store on firebase and start using
it a quick technical question did you
end up using fire store or real-time for
information no so be slightly more
functionality and the other is faster I
think something that they did redone
good article about it I don't know all
the eggs
I'm preferably a fire store right now
usually yeah fire store the real-time
firebases is slightly faster but most of
the time we don't need that sub-second
response time
and collaborate firestorm yes and the
good thing about Firestar is it handles
not only data itself about user
authentication and it has a quite
extensive list of what it can use for
the authentication ways so it can we can
connect the application to Facebook to
Google to linked into some they actually
doesn't have and they don't have
LinkedIn on there I found that you can't
do it but they don't have it as a
prebuilt one because i was just looking
at it yesterday and I was like I thought
LinkedIn was in the list I don't know if
they took it out oh yeah there was oh
okay yeah I just thought I'd mention
that because I didn't meant into before
he came on that I was helping a friend
and we wanted LinkedIn login and that
was one of the challenges is that they
don't have it there's a there's a tool
where you can set it up whoo-hoo no
LinkedIn you need in that bizarre I
think maybe linkedin's because its face
because it's Microsoft okay so yeah and
it's just easy and quick to and it's
better to not have to call back end for
just blows back it works and it's free
as well so have not paid to do the
marketing for them but yeah very good
so that initially I didn't use github to
put the code on because we didn't
discuss exactly when it's during to the
open source so it's private
and and github does allow free two or
three free private repos now so you
can't put it on there as well
yeah change if you're not already using
up here I did have a link to using any
terms that need to be explained you
might help us remember I vaguely
understand I mean I know you know sort
of the code repositories and that getup
tends to be more popular one the whole
like private versus open sorts thing I I
was not aware what was anything with
that so that's interesting yeah yeah for
the the near future like it won't be
open source to start with until actually
starts working and then you know if the
community says hey we'd like for these
parts to be open source then we can
definitely explore it but this whole
thing like it's a pretty big emphasis at
least later on down the road for like
privacy and security and I have some
projects managed to you know walk that
line fine still be open source in
private and secure but I'll probably
wait until them sort of more down the
road and actually have like staff and
and more like dedicated security people
to figure out how that works in what
should and shouldn't be open source
generally it's better to go open source
because you have people who source
products are known to be much more
secure because they are open because
people are generally nice enough so when
they see a bug they tell you instead of
exploiting it hopefully hmm but yeah the
history shows that open source security
wise is the way to go but yeah I do
think there that will end up that way in
sort of
with the end goal being as transparent
as reasonably possible which I think
open source is it's definitely a part of
that the thing that I don't know of an
open source
I mean maybe like Firefox or Linux might
kind of get to this well it's like if
this is actually successful it people
will be trying to game it at like the
level of trying to game Facebook or
Twitter or something that right like if
your goal is to be able to sort of bend
the data to your will you know if if
that thing works I think having a fully
exposed like know exactly how the guts
work helps with that like how Google
does it make their their algorithm
public it's quite the opposite and so I
think it's going to end up being
abundant at this point so it was made
efficient open source which we aren't
reinventing any wheels here so I'm not
too too worried yet but like I'm more
thinking down the road like long term so
yeah if it's especially if all the
components that were using are resource
as you said by definition it could kind
of already yes okay so that's about the
choices should we go into the crowd and
technical choices inside of the
application itself oh I don't know if we
want to get to I think yeah yeah I think
I think this is a good level here so
maybe if we want to go ahead and look at
the UI and and people can see the
feedback between you and Adrienne oh
yeah I've done a little bit of feedback
but just la get I think if y'all don't
mind just having other people see what
it's like to work with rival upper right
and now it is very early days so seeing
what a very early days prototype looks
like so you don't get scared away yeah
it's like a lot of stuff is hard-coded
which completely makes sense for the
very very first version now the question
is because I am string art I can't share
screen all right now yeah I can probably
share the spring and you can share it
though just let me see a screen option I
was going to have the prototype ready
like for this meeting which is added
much some functionality it's not ready
[Music]
and yeah that's the one yeah for those
watching never ever do a build wall
doing Marcy she's gonna do it but don't
do it don't do like Marty's right it's
risky don't do it don't do it after 5
p.m. just don't just nothing can go
wrong it will at some point yeah I think
at this point it's not like this is
mission critical for anything so it's
not too too worrisome but yeah I think
that's a safe a safe standard to employ
and I prefer to not have to in the
middle of life demo see any bugs and
yeah okay it's oh is this the new
version with these how many changes
there we discussed yes yeah I think I
didn't hear the first part of that or
you guys may have been talking sorry you
know code speak and so I was like I saw
you guys get to the point where like yet
don't release it indeed you know in
these situations now make sense why that
came up okay and now I did what I said I
should not yes it is it's working for me
refresh the page and yeah I just
realized I left it
by default on the people venture but you
still see the home screen right then you
have small links linking to the list of
organizations because these are the two
initially these are the two main sort
local channels right people and the
organizations they belong to they work
for they have an affiliation with stuff
like that okay
mmm so the difference between the
previous version and this version is you
have working sign up or sign in button
right yes that's the one and you can
right now even create your account okay
cool do that yeah because stop sharing
just want to do doing its more so that I
don't have my email recorded and
streamed yep yeah it's funny sometimes
on screen sharing goes wrong to show too
much so more to show is doing that maybe
I can ask you a couple of technical
questions and hopefully this won't be
too technical but it looks like you're
not using like react route or anything
in this no not at this moment it's one
page application though I'm going to of
course rockin as well of the next three
phones quicker just add the drop-down
menu at the top yeah and you're not
using a bootstrap or anything like that
have you decided whether you get to do
all custom CSS or are you gonna try and
use something I got CSS to minimum so it
can be extend
when the prototype is ready to be looked
at my thumb someone who knows graphics
and proper design yeah so we shouldn't
be analyzing it for like mobile
performance and stuff like that
no it's not the responsible but it could
be yes which once I sort of got a vibe
for how it actually flows it did
technically to work on my cell phone I
just wasn't used to sort of seeing and
that was the first time I viewed it but
then after I saw it on desktop I went
back computer on mobile and my co this
actually it works I'm sure it needs some
tweaks but like a loads and you can use
it which that's quite reasonable in my
mind oh it's just yeah which I mean I
didn't start this from like let's be
mobile first like right now I'm just
trying to get sort of the data base and
proof of concept it'll end up needing to
to to be mobile but that isn't the first
concern right now so I created the user
I see and so if I go you're right so now
I'm on the home page and this will end
up you know sort of being a fancier like
way to visualize different things but
for now this is exactly what I asked for
just the list of people in organisations
so from there I can go to people just me
are there I've got the one record yeah
and this is actually people are now kept
in in firebase in backhanded that so
this record comes straight from the
database which is a good start and now
I'm going to quickly change your access
to I mean okay thanks and if you reload
the page
[Music]
in money you are hopefully going to see
people and organizations and users okay
users is what is the least all thank you
I am NOT because okay
I used my local version of this so here
there will be a list of accounts of
users of recollection and there are two
types of user 1 and so it only and one
is ugly
and I think and articles and edit them
so now if you go back to the people I
see if you choose to edit or I can add
new person like I just see it and if I
go back oh no so yeah and if you're
you've got you can add our city of it do
I need to refresh this page once a new
person
children's committee that's the last
thing I added to behold anything so
hopefully it will work well shows right
now perfect yes he's good to get away
from and then I can go to my Jones and
now it's got that stuff cool so this is
working having the same thing for
organizations that's going to be easy
because it's basically the same same
thing just slightly different data so
we're history that is hard-coded right
now yes it is because the idea is once
both people and organization
organizations come from the database
then I will have some way of connecting
one to the other right
and then the records will reflect what
is in the database
perfect yeah and I think this is what
the NDP should look like monomers yeah I
mean this is cool very mean hair very
close to what I had in mind actually
looks really close to the markups yeah I
tried to style it as Oh simple but as as
the documentation showed right that's
usually yeah our waters the way to do it
is basically MVP contains like initial
screenshots and images of we think how
it should look like and then it can be
coded and that they it may be made real
and then you have the demo looking more
or less like the mock-ups from the first
iteration and then you have something to
work on and get feedback and think what
can be done better
and if it's what you wanted oh there is
something to improve change remove
certain ones I can just shrimp ring up
the mock-up so I can actually show sort
of what the starting thing was so yeah
that's why I do this so these are the
mock-ups that we sort of started with so
you can see the homepage here right we
start with just the name of they have up
here I think that image may have moved I
think that was originally over here but
not sure what happened the menu as you
can see I mean that's very close to this
menu here and I like your clothes better
what before it actually shows the word
that's what I had in mind it was just a
bit harder to do in this we have the
search bar and then logged in so you can
tell that's very close to the top bar
there that's all the elements were there
if we go back to home or you've got the
list of people in organizations yet the
people and election's just find this was
an old mock-up where I changed what
objects were actually in the MVB so that
that matches it and then you go to
something like people where it's just
the list I thought that in these
mock-ups I had an actual person detail
but I think that may have been a
different mock-up that go at it but just
so that people can see so that's what I
started off as and the the current
version Matushka made is pretty darn
close sweet we've kind of estimated a
couple of weeks for this how are you
doing on that timeline is it going
faster or slower
I think what's the estimation for a
full-time a couple of weeks yeah okay so
what you so right now took me about a
shelf at 15 to 20 hours okay yeah so and
in your head are the discussions though
and stuff so that could have changed the
requirement stuff but it sounds like
you're well within the estimate which of
course everyone needs to remember
estimates are always wrong that's why
they were called estimate yes just to
give you a ballpark but yeah it looks
like yeah just to give kind of people an
idea
the estimation process and in this case
Adriel created some pretty detailed
specs and more toosh estimated and I
just took a look at it and agreed with
the estimate oftentimes though Adriel
though you you have experience doing
specifications and stuff yeah so that
might be a little different for our on
technical person that hasn't worked and
the thing at all that right you may be
describing what you want and then
depending on the developer or if you can
hire our project manager they may be
helping you kind of make mock-ups and
then the kind of the cost would kind of
go up from there just a drill had some
skills that brought down the cost yeah
that's a good call out and I do find
that like even people who've you know
don't necessarily have a history of
product management I think you know if
you can sort of sketch what you want on
paper and then and I think the app that
I'm using here called mock-ups but with
a queue moq UPS there's a ton of them
out there but the test one I've been
using they make it pretty easy to sort
of you know drag out your elements
commit to make it see how you look yeah
in my experience this is one of the most
useful things to be able to give to a
developer so you can like this is a
pretty you know loaded page as far as
you can see the banner up top you can
see the tabs you can see the list you
can see a grid it's like to open you can
you know the whole like a picture's
worth a thousand words thing that's
probably a bitty you know Hollen free
there is a free version I believe yeah I
I'm using the the paid version here but
if for whatever reason it's not free
there I would bet money that there's
going to be ten free ones out there if
you saw one at work people we're using
that has a I think you think they have a
pretty decent option called Sigma fi GMA
that one seemed to to be nice because on
this it's sort of each page is its own
thing and you click between them on that
it's like you've still got your
individual page but then you zoom oh and
it shows all the pages and kind of how
it flows which I quite liked for trying
to understand and you can even make it
tour certain places when you click it'll
go to the
the other page I think so yeah which I
can technically do in this too but I do
like the like zooming out canvas view of
pages I do like that more yeah and just
a word of caution I do have a friend who
was working with a company and she paid
a fair amount of money and she said a
working prototype and they got her they
gave her a figma and oh so it really you
know it's you can't it doesn't actually
do anything so she was really and she
was pretty sure that that she was clear
that this was not even a working
prototype this was supposed to be a
working app right
based on her requirements okay that's
already you know not even what I would
call a prototype but well I guess it
does fit on the term prototype yeah so
be be cautious out there yeah and I'm
good I just checked because what I had
for the requirements and the mock-ups I
took from my collection
drafts back right just specs which
contains no link to the what I'm seeing
right now so for the record alright I
made sure everyone's right yeah I
totally forgot about that I I made these
and then okay that's a good point
I'm gonna go find that one just to see
so that actually means that material
even better because the ones that I
really weren't that nice ones like where
are they great great minds think alike
so yeah this one I just yeah so did this
like I just use Google draw so I just
actually did like you know insert draw
and then you can editor here so it's not
nearly as nice looking as the other one
but it did it let me sort of more easily
embed it in the text field and you can
see here like so person the one that you
created so this is what was made and
that's what was asked you can see the
version diminution made is a hell of a
lot nicer looking thank you but it's not
as nice as the
before well yeah it's now that the code
is there and styling is yeah it's
totally adjustable
so I mmm
I'm even too too worried about how it
looks yeah I kind of want to get it to
like the MVP stage and and then I've got
people who are quite good at branding
and making things look nice
I don't want to spend any time on that
until like the structure and skeleton is
there because you know I mean as I'm
sure we've all seen projects change when
you're sort of in the middle of them and
I'm going into this knowing that like
hey I'm gonna change my mind and B I
didn't do a perfect job at explaining
everything and and that's on me so you
know if it ends up being like you build
something that wasn't quite what what
well I explained I'm going to assume was
probably my fault in this case cuz I
didn't owe as much time is like when
I've done this for work before I spend
10 times longer and it was you know in
painstaking agonizing for both me and
the developer detail which if I can get
up away with avoiding that I will take
that off and besides when you just have
the initial idea and then you know
through stages to get to how you think
the MVP should look like the ultimate
test for everything is reality
and once the thing is created then you
can see and compare it to what you know
then after getting feedback only then
you see how what is really needed and
whether and to what extent your idea is
fulfilling this like yeah it's not
possible to foresee all the
circumstances and details beforehand so
you have to have an MVP and then go
wrong there but MVP is this important
yeah just a starting point which is an
important thing to remember and going
into it I sort of because I've been down
this road I know that the MVP won't
actually be what I have in mind right
now and that's just because that's how
reality works right like as we go
through it you might be like actually
that's super hard to do it this way I
can do it in a tenth of the time if I do
it this way instead
okay sure that's probably it could trade
off and just you know after I see it on
a page I'm like oh I didn't think it was
you know gonna do that and I forgot that
this would be on top of that and how it
works so it's like that sort of where
I'm coming from I think that that's an
important thing for somebody who's in my
role who's not the developer to keep in
mind like it's on you if you're in my
role to sort of make sure you explain it
right and if it's not like in
painstaking detail realized that that
was on you and sofas slightly off yes
whose fault it is because I do know that
when I hear people planning things it
seems a lot like you know it's a hundred
percent they think that that's how it's
going to be and I think any product
manager or developer that hears that you
can be pretty safe oh you've never done
this before if you think that it's going
to go end to end and there's gonna be no
changes and you're gonna have it exactly
planned right from step one almost never
those things you know spiraling the
first iteration and then based on the
first iteration you can and only then
you can see what's to improve because
it's just not possible to ever make a
project that good sort of goes to the
production stage to the final stage
unchanged usually the changes are
anything from wide out to huge and
sometimes it's sometimes halfway through
you'll see that the idea was not even
yeah sometimes it happens yeah and I
think like that at its core is one of
the reasons why I like agile is because
you know you're you're you're you may
still be planning down
the road but you're gonna see it how it
changes week over week and then after a
month and a half you can be like oh
actually maybe we need to pivot a bit
mm no that I'm actually seeing it be
developed and testing it and trying it
out turns out maybe we need to adjust a
bit and they keep going down the
slightly altered road so what are the
next steps for this prototype or this so
one of the things that I want to do is
to sort of get on its own I guess
development environment I think it was
mo Tuesday they recommended that I go
with digitalocean which I did some
research on and that sounded quite good
sort of start to set that up and so to
get it like a on a you know a
environment where I'm not leeching out
of your resources and then also to get
it to the point where it's actually on
its own domain name or I guess in this
case a a subdomain so the I I think the
initial idea is like f dot wiki election
comm would then go here and you know
even though it's still early days of
course as we go through the agile
releases that will sort of always be the
current version of the prototype until
it's an actual app and then it'll be the
app cool or teach I wonder if you to
explain to us and the viewers any
reasons why my chosen digitalocean
I'm just curious because I used in the
past it compares to amazing digital
option is less complicated in initial
setup and if you need the full power of
another cloud you then but otherwise
digital option is the price wise it's I
think it's well depending on but it's
cheaper is at least as fast as AWS and
it's like the second respectable cloud
provider
in a cloud space and if choice miles it
is it auto-scale I think I've from the
brief amount of research I did aid like
they seem to have fewer options which in
that case what was good as I tried to go
shopping you know like figuring out how
much I was good going to pick on Amazon
and that process is ridiculous like I
was trying to get to the lowest tier
price and it was still like for the app
hosting was super cheap but then the
database part to keep being like five
thousand dollars they'd be like I don't
think that's the lowest price T er but
it didn't quite work properly and the
pricing on digital ocean seemed way
clear and then the other part that that
I like is that it's not Amazon where I
can avoid put any money in just his
pocket all air on that side usually but
yeah I was the only other I haven't
looked at a lot of posters recently I've
used Microsoft in the past which is
another big tech company and then dangit
I forgot the one I was gonna go to
there's a a serverless kind of provider
hey uh if I can think of the name I'll
bring it back up but but yeah digital
digital ocean sounds um sounds good I
have not used them yet but they look
really good and they do have you know I
I was the aggressive marketing but like
fairly centered marketing where as soon
as I visited them I saw ads for them on
Facebook and YouTube for like two weeks
so I mean it's at least it was relevant
and I got to learn a bit more about them
through their ad so it wasn't too bad
but uh be aware of that if that happens
to be something about this year a couple
of years ago I when I was looking for
new provider for my services I took
different providers and it seemed like
the pricing is similar we know that AWS
is of course the biggest and the
probably most well obviously most use
but
we the biggest set of you know the most
powerful and you can configure anything
and its scalability and everything yeah
but the gel option was on this very
strong second place and better when all
you wanted is they seemed to simple VPS
and no they given the other do it as so
that was my choice and I use them for so
there are other projects and they are I
guess big enough to be a stable enough
though these days probably
they all are stable to some extent and
it's matter of preference more than
anything I guess but I was never
disappointed with that services so I
stayed with them and used them for this
project as well I guess the one I want
to look at is net laugh i but they host
hosting environment right so we can
provide appears all do they I don't know
well yeah it's hosting what do you want
of VPS because of my background okay
yeah I mean I would rather and this is
I'm not saying that's the best thing but
I would I would rather go with a
scalable hosting provider although
honestly if you're doing a single page
app with with using and then using a
back-end like far store then you really
don't need you know a content delivery
system is probably the best place to
host the actual code right so sure okay
yeah so that's kind of why I do net will
find not that it's sir list but it's
yeah it's just static files but
and then they give you the yeah but I
but I'm not as familiar with it so you
definitely it's good to go with the
technology or familiar with mmm I have
to learn the new thing I did here of
course about that if I I just I'm not
very familiar with what it is exactly
they go and how it compares to the PPSS
I worked with in the past one thing that
came up in some other project was when I
wanted to have Oh almost which is the
authentication mechanism using github
for an application the way it works is
you have to have a sound secure space
somewhere so we can store the key of the
like application application key that
you used to connect to github it's like
three points thing together in
authorization yeah and then I didn't
need IDPs I'm not sure if not if I
solved this and how exactly but yeah
there's sometimes you need a back-end so
for them they would they would they
would have a us I think they support
server less code but yeah but you could
also do that and fire store with the
firestore thing yeah so there's lots of
there's lots of solutions so yeah so now
the new hotness in that area would be
using lambdas or you know little bitty
bits of node running on a server
somewhere so that would also be without
a virtual private server but it would be
I can't read the term right now lambdas
one of the names I can't read the
generic term form but serverless
functions yes or less function would be
one way to go around it
in the last it's
Monsoor something I haven't always go
ipfs yes so we got a couple more minutes
I don't know if anyone has any other
closing comments I want to wrap one
thing I did want to mention I'm not sure
if this is easy to change later or if
it's something we have to you know if it
makes it way easier to plan for now but
with the whole single page app thing
does that mean it like no matter what
record of content you you're viewing the
URL would still just be like after the
election to calm yeah and the idea is to
not use URLs at all we see in the
application don't need them well sorry
the idea is for the web page to never
reload so click on the link and stuff
happens but the application itself stays
in place on your screen and those
changes on the screen is just what you
want to change right and then yes I'm
just saying it I think I drew want the
deep linking URLs though which are about
that talked about I think that's
different from it's going to be one page
up anyway but I am going to add the
links because the links are necessary if
you want to send link to someone linking
to the one particular record on the
bathroom right yeah we'll be there
that's okay perfect I want to make sure
it's said that's a pretty important part
for the deep linking because you know
you find a cool page on a certain
politician or a certain thing you want
to be able you know to share it on
Facebook or email it or do what else so
the links in this case would it would be
after that last slasher to be a hash
which it actually has on the website
right now I think it's a hash and then
when you change that that hash would
keeps changing so if you copied it out
of the URL and paste it in an email it
would take them to the same spot right
Artesia
yeah I see so that's like oh it's not
working right now though Oh
he just hasn't yeah he didn't and I'd
asked him at the beginning part of that
would be a tool react router but yeah
yeah it's something he'll add in a
little later nice and then that will
have more control over sort of how that
URL structured for the deep linking yeah
yes okay perfect yeah cuz I think in the
control in the initial wrote for
requirements I think it was sort of
hidden in the text for each section it
gives an example of like the ideal URL
where it's just like yeah I guess the
the preface to to the ID so it's like
the string and then if the ID is just
like you know a text string that's fine
too it doesn't have to be like the
person's name or the action name or
anything well though sometimes you'll
you'll have it to be an ID and then a
slash and just put the name of it so
that you get stuff but but the system
will ignore that here's the ID that the
way if you change the name the links
don't all break right hyojong yeah
that's one way to do it I'm not sure
what my teachers thought about that yet
I haven't decided I'm because search
engine optimization so you google your
favorite politician you got the link to
a collection and precisely to the
specific information about the person
Steve also mentioned Heroku in the chat
that's something that gets some respect
with coder groups and yes maybe lets you
build for free all of these yeah
I'm not actually sure yet what it is I
know that yeah we're like older work
ways Salesforce Heroku came up a fair
bit I haven't actually used it but I
haven't tried to use it for hand like
building the websites for free and stuff
but that's good and is that parties at
some pinnable AWS says that one seemed
very useful saying AWS has meant for
sort of enterprise scaling for
technology which I think you know I
would agree with a lot of the huge apps
to use AWS for their backbone and then
he's saying maybe don't bother with them
unless you've actually got a fair amount
of traffic and yeah Desmond
Amazon a crap ton of money yeah but even
the smaller hosts are now able to
support scaling and a lot of that
infrastructure has been democratized
right so I would even still kind of
suggest to reach out to smaller there's
very few companies that would need that
and if you're that big a Polish good to
be doing cross cloud anyways so ideally
and sometimes even companies I worked
for in the past that and when you have
not enough up too much traffic or not
enough bandwidth sometimes it's helpful
to rethink your strategy about content
delivery as in to check you have images
like within a reasonable range of size
because sometimes I saw web pages that
the code of the web page itself was just
a couple of kilobytes and it was very
fast and didn't saturate the bandwidth
and a dangerous extent but then the
background was an image ten megabytes in
size so yeah is a cool subject yes
yeah and that will definitely end up
being important but / / / now I'm not
too terribly worried but let's you know
we'll well all work together to stay
away from any 10 megabyte bitmaps and
that should help us out I guess we're
out of time yeah that's anyone think we
covered a fair bit here that's good I
guess we can't end the streaming and
wrap up anything we want to say off
stream after that so thank you everyone
for joining I imagine there will be more
of these going forward as we get further
along with this prototype so you can
watch as we go and learn from any you
know mistakes or cool stuff that we end
up doing so